Clifford Kennedy Berryman Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Clifford Kennedy Berryman Papers 1814-1965 (bulk 1890-1949)
MSS12559
Berryman, Clifford Kennedy, 1869-1949
1,000 items
4 containers
1.6 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Cartoonist. Correspondence, drawings, printed matter, invitations, photographs, and a speech relating primarily to Berryman's career as a political cartoonist for the Washington Post and the Washington Star.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Berryman, Clifford Kennedy, 1869-1949.; Bittinger, Charles, 1879-1970--Correspondence.; Cleveland, Grover, 1837-1908.; Coolidge, Calvin, 1872-1933.; Eisenhower, Dwight D. (Dwight David), 1890-1969.; Harding, Warren G. (Warren Gamaliel), 1865-1923.; Hoover, Herbert, 1874-1964.; McCutcheon, John T. (John Tinney), 1870-1949--Correspondence.; McKinley, William, 1843-1901.; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945.; Roosevelt, Theodore, 1858-1919.; Taft, William H. (William Howard), 1857-1930.; Truman, Harry S., 1884-1972.; Wilson, Woodrow, 1856-1924.
Organizations
United States. Congress.; United States. Supreme Court.
Subjects
American newspapers--Washington (D.C.); Cabinet officers--Correspondence.; Judges--United States--Correspondence.; Legislators--United States--Correspondence.; Political cartoons.; Presidents--United States--Autographs.; Presidents--United States--Correspondence.; Presidents--United States--Portraits.; Slave bills of sale.; Teddy bears.; Vice-Presidents--United States--Correspondence.
Places
United States--Politics and government--Caricatures and cartoons.
Titles
Washington post.; Washington star.
Occupations
Cartoonists.
Provenance
The papers of Clifford Kennedy Berryman, cartoonist, were given to the Library of Congress by his daughter, Florence Berryman, between 1964 and 1971.
Transfers
Items have been transferred from the Manuscript Division to other custodial divisions of the Library. Some cartoons, drawings, and sketches have been transferred to the Prints and Photographs Division. A phonograph record has been transferred to the Recorded Sound Section of the Motion Picture, Broadcasting, and Recorded Sound Division. All transfers are identified in these divisions as part of the Clifford Kennedy Berryman Papers.
Other Repositories
Other collections of Clifford Kennedy Berryman material are located in the Historical Society of Washington, D.C., and the Prints and Photographs Division of the Library of Congress.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Clifford Kennedy Berryman are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1869, Apr. 2 Born, Woodford County, Kentucky
1886 1891 Draftsman, United States Patent Office, Washington, D.C.
1891 1907 Cartoonist, Washington Post
1893 Married Kate G. Durfee
1902 Originated the Teddy Bear in a cartoon of an incident involving Theodore Roosevelt (1858-1919) and a small bear
1907 1949 Cartoonist, Washington Star
1944 Awarded Pulitzer Prize for editorial cartooning
1949, Dec. 11 Died, Washington, D.C.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Clifford Kennedy Berryman (1869-1949) span the years 1814-1965, with the bulk of the material dating from 1890 to 1949. The papers relate primarily to his career as a political cartoonist for the Washington Post and the Washington Star that spanned more than fifty years.
A large portion of the papers consists of letters Berryman received from presidents, vice presidents, cabinet members, members of Congress, Supreme Court justices, and other prominent Americans. Many correspondents commented on specific cartoons and thanked Berryman for his gift of the originals. Also included are letters from fellow illustrators, including Charles Bittinger and John T. McCutcheon. Among a small section of letters sent by Berryman are illustrated letters he wrote to his mother during the time he was working in the United States Patent Office.
Other items include drafts of a lecture, “The Origin, Development and Influence of the Cartoon,” that Berryman delivered to the Literary Society of Washington in 1921. The drafts contain sketches in the margins and are accompanied by pencil sketches that later were enlarged to be visible from the lecture platform. Two autograph albums contain pen portraits of approximately 120 prominent Americans dating from 1898 to 1949. Each portrait is autographed by the subject. Among those represented in the albums are presidents Grover Cleveland, Calvin Coolidge, Dwight D. Eisenhower, Warren G. Harding, Herbert Hoover, William McKinley, Franklin D. Roosevelt, Theodore Roosevelt (next to a sketch of the Teddy Bear), William H. Taft, Harry S. Truman, and Woodrow Wilson. Printed matter includes items relating to the Gridiron Club.
One item unrelated to Clifford Berryman’s career is an 1814 bill of sale for a woman and child. The transaction was conducted between Berryman family members.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged by type of material and therein by name of person, subject, organization, or public office.
Container List
- Letters sent (Box 1)
  - To mother, Sallie C. Berryman, 1890, 1894 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1898-1945 (Box 1)
- Letters received (Box 1)
  - Presidents (Box 1)
  - Vice presidents (Box 1)
  - Wilson, Woodrow, cabinet members (Box 1)
  - Roosevelt, Franklin D., administration (Box 1)
    - Administrators (Box 1)
    - Cabinet members (Box 1)
  - Truman, Harry S., administration (Box 1)
  - Various cabinet members (Box 1)
  - United States senators (Box 1)
  - United States representatives (Box 1)
  - Speakers of the House of Representatives and justices of the Supreme Court (Box 1)
  - Democratic National Committee and Republican National Committee (Box 1)
  - Schley, Winfield Scott, court of inquiry (1901) (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
    - A-K (Box 2)
    - L-W (Box 2)
  - Fellow illustrators (Box 2)
  - Berryman birthdays (Box 2)
    - Seventieth, 1939 (Box 2)
    - Eightieth, 1949 (Box 2)
  - Blackburn, Joseph C.S., portrait (Box 2)
  - Darling, Jay N., dinner (Box 2)
  - Literary Society of Washington (Box 2)
  - Unidentified (Box 3)
- Miscellany (Box 3)
  - Autograph books containing autographed pen and ink portraits, 1898-1949, (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Bill of sale for slaves, 1814 (Box 3)
  - Invitations (Box 3)
  - Programs, (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Speech, 1921, (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Printed matter (Box 4)